<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>README</title>

    <subtitle>Version<?eval ${project.version}?></subtitle>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Charles</firstname><surname>Loomis</surname></personname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS)</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <abstract>
      <para>This document describes important changes in the pan configuration
      language compiler between the v9 series and previous releases.</para>
    </abstract>

    <productnumber><?eval ${project.version}?></productnumber>

    <date><?eval ${buildTimestamp}?></date>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>License</title>

    <para>Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"). You
    may obtain a copy of the License at <uri
    xlink:href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0"
    xlink:type="simple">http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0</uri>.
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT
    WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the
    License for the specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Migration Issues</title>

    <section>
      <title>Deprecated Features</title>

      <para>All of the deprecated features in the v8 series of the compilers
      has been removed from the v9 series. Ensure that your configuration
      compiles with the deprecation warnings activated with the v8 compiler
      before migrating to the v9 series.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>ChangeLog</title>

    <section>
      <title>Version 9.1</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>(SF Bug #3483938) Fix the README file to contain information
          on changes up through the production 9.0 release.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Version 9.0</title>

      <para>Production release contains the same features as RC3. All version
      numbers will be considered production releases unless marked explicitly
      as alpha, beta, or release candidates. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Version 9.0.0-RC3</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>(SF RFE #3422390) The root element used as the starting point
          for all machine profiles can be specified from the command line and
          ant task. This allows the injection of data into all of the profiles
          without having to include explicitly a template in all machine
          profiles. This will be useful for injecting build metadata into the
          profiles. Note that the injected data must still follow the global
          schema (if defined), otherwise builds will fail with validation
          errors. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Version 9.0.0-RC2</title>

      <para>The documentation has been significantly reorganized with all of
      the documentation apart from this README combined into a single "pan
      book".</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Version 9.0.0-RC1</title>

      <para>This release contains the following changes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>(SF Bug #3171788) Improve error message for format() function
          when there is a mismatch between given format string and
          arguments.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>(SF RFE #3386906) Support for \b (backspace) and \f (form
          feed) escape sequences in double-quoted strings.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>(SF Bug #3186921) Dependency calculation in ant task does not
          work correctly for namespaced object templates.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
